export const GOVERNMENTA2013 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Government can be defined as the study of",
A: "constitutions",
B: "cabinet system of government only",
C: "how people rule themselves",
D: "presidential system of government only",
answer: "C. how people rule themselves",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Which of the following is a feature of a state?",
A: "Pursuance of sectional interest",
B: "Colonial expericnce",
C: "Territorial boundary",
D: "Temporary existence",
answer: "C. Territorial boundary",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. As a political ideology, communism seeks to",
A: "accumulate capital in the hands of a few",
B: "accommodate division of citizens into classes",
C: "eliminate all forms of socio-economic inequalities",
D: "create economic opportunities for profit making",
answer: "C. eliminate all forms of socio-economic inequalities",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. Totalitarianism means a government headed by",
A: "a dictor",
B: "wealthy people",
C: "educated elite",
D: "the masses",
answer: "A. a dictor",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. Monarchy means government",
A: "headed by a king",
B: "by the people",
C: "of the majority",
D: "run by the elite",
answer: "A. headed by a king",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. The rule of law is observed when",
A: "democracy is practised",
B: "laws are kept scret",
C: "revolution is encouraged",
D: "only the elite can govern",
answer: "A. democracy is practised",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Delegated legislation is necessary because it",
A: "helps to promote dictatorship",
B: "prevents even development",
C: "is useful in times of emergency",
D: "gives a lot of power to the president",
answer: "C. useful in times of emergency",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. One of the criticisms against delegated legislation is that it",
A: "promotes separation of powers",
B: "is not parctised in advanced countries",
C: "encroaches on parliamentary power",
D: "gives too much power to the judicary",
answer: "C. encroaches on parliamentary power",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Fundamental Human Rights seek to",
A: "promote the dignity of man",
B: "train political activists",
C: "encourages economic activities",
D: "enthrone mob rule",
answer: "A. promote the dignity of man",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Constitutionalism implies that",
A: "citizens should read the constitution always",
B: "leaders should ignore the dictates of the constitution",
C: "citizens should challenge the provisions of the constitution",
D: "*******************************",
answer: "Z. zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz (This option is missing)",
correctLetter: "Z",
correctOption: 9,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following is not a source of a country’s constitution?",
A: "Legislative decisions",
B: "past contitutions",
C: "writ of Mandamus",
D: "Judicial precedents",
answer: "C. writ of Mandamus",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. which of the following is not within the scope of a constitution?",
A: "Fundamental Human Rights",
B: "Organs of government",
C: "Coup d’etat",
D: "Preamble",
answer: "C. Coup d’etat",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Centralization of power is a feature of a",
A: "federal system",
B: "unitary system",
C: "confederal system",
D: "presidential system",
answer: "B. unitary system",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. In a unitary state, governmental powers are concentrated at the",
A: "component units",
B: "local level",
C: "centre",
D: "regions",
answer: "C. centre",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Which of the following is true of a parliamentary system of government?",
A: "there is an Executive President",
B: "Fusion of powers is discouraged",
C: "Collective responsibility is emphasized",
D: "The Prime Minister is the head of the judiciary",
answer: "C. Collective responsibility is emphasized",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. The system of government in which the president acts as the head of state and the head of government is",
A: "diarchy",
B: "Presidential",
C: "unitary",
D: "parliamentary",
answer: "B. Presidential",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Which of the following is a factor in the formation of a federation?",
A: "Desire for a union",
B: "Absence of a common enemy",
C: "Small population",
D: "Geographical incontiguity",
answer: "A. Desire for a union",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Which of the following is a feature of a confederation?",
A: "it has a rigid constitution",
B: "the central government is stronger than the component units",
C: "there is a legal right of secession",
D: "there is no provision for a state constitution",
answer: "C. there is a legal right of secession",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The formation and implementation of policies are the major duties of the",
A: "police",
B: "judicary",
C: "executive",
D: "legislature",
answer: "C. executive",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Bicameralism is adopted because it",
A: "guards against intra-party clashes",
B: "prevents arbitary law making",
C: "projects party manifestoes",
D: "is the only system available",
answer: "B. prevents arbitary law making",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Parliamentary filibuster refers to a",
A: "a procedure of impeachng the president",
B: "delay method of prolonging debates in parliament",
C: "process of passing bills into law",
D: "a special way of initiating money bills",
answer: "B. delay method of prolonging debates in parliament",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Which of the following functions is performed by the executive?",
A: "Recruitment of judges",
B: "Passing of bills to laws",
C: "Adjudication of cases",
D: "Implementation of policies",
answer: "D. Implementation of policies",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. When a court of law declares an action of the executive ultra-vires , it implies that",
A: "the action is illegal and above the power given",
B: "the executive has to implement the action",
C: "such an action should be passed into law",
D: "only the legislature can deal with such an action",
answer: "A. the action is illegal and above the power given",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Which of the following is a duty of a good citizen?",
A: "paying tax regularly",
B: "Must assist the poor",
C: "should challenge the of the land",
D: "Must join the law enforcement agents",
answer: "A. paying tax regularly",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Citizens can be deprived of their rights during",
A: "democratic regime",
B: "parliamentary debate",
C: "emergency periods",
D: "political campaigns",
answer: "C. emergency periods",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Which of the following is an obligation of a citizen?",
A: "Arresting offenders",
B: "Voting at elections",
C: "Prosecuting offenders",
D: "Adjudicating cases",
answer: "B. Voting at elections",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. A multi-party system often leads to the formation of a",
A: "coalition government",
B: "very strong executive",
C: "dictatoral government",
D: "confederal government",
answer: "A. dictatorship",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Which of the following is not a function of a political party?",
A: "Educating the government",
B: "Interest articulation",
C: "Aggregation of opinions",
D: "Selection of persons for gobvernment",
answer: "B. multi-party",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Franchise means the right of all qualified citizens to",
A: "manipulate election results",
B: "conduct elections",
C: "enforec electoral laws",
D: "vote and be voted for",
answer: "A. coalition",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The geographical units into which a country is divided for the purpose of election are called",
A: "states",
B: "constituencies",
C: "polling areas",
D: "county councils",
answer: "A. democratic government",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. One way to ensure a free and fair election is to",
A: "operate a one-party system",
B: "allow parties to campaign on election day",
C: "guarantee the security of electoral officers and materials",
D: "appoint a politician as the chairman of the electoral commission",
answer: "B. it ensures the anonymity of the voter",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. An election that involves the use of an electoral college is",
A: "run-off election",
B: "a general election",
C: "an open balloting",
D: "an indirect election",
answer: "C. simple majority system",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Which of the following functions is performed by the electoral commission?",
A: "Distribution of party membership cards",
B: "Presenting parties manifestoes",
C: "Delimiting the country into constituencies",
D: "Conducting oath of office for elected president",
answer: "A. political equality",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Which of the following statements distinguishes political parties from pressure groups?",
A: "Political parties only lobby government to change certain policies",
B: "Pressure groups select candidates for political of fices",
C: "Political parties influence government policies",
D: "Pressure groups influence government policies to member’s interest",
answer: "B. free press",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Public opinion enables a government to",
A: "influence the public",
B: "Suppress its opponents",
C: "cut down the coat of governing",
D: "know the feeling of the masses",
answer: "C. formulating and executing public policies",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. The anonymity in the civil service means that a civil servant",
A: "is above the law of the land",
B: "receives neither praise nor blame",
C: "should take part in partisan politics",
D: "should not be disciplined for any misconduct",
answer: "A. political patronage",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Which of the following is a problem of civil service?",
A: "Red-tapism",
B: "Offering professional advice to political leaders",
C: "Continuous keeping of records",
D: "Changing of government through election",
answer: "B. Board of Directors",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Public corporations are Set Up by",
A: "a minister",
B: "a director",
C: "a permanent secretary",
D: "an act of parliament",
answer: "D. set up to provide essential services",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Which of the following is true of a Public Corporation it is?",
A: "established by a bye-law",
B: "owned by the minister of finance",
C: "set up to make profit for share holders",
D: "set up to provide essential services",
answer: "A. bring government nearer to the people",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. All the following are established to",
A: "bring government nearer to the people",
B: "give more powers to the traditional rulers",
C: "make people less loyal to the central government",
D: "make central government interfere in local affairs",
answer: "D. an area acquired by the colonialists through settlement or conquest",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. All the following are problems facing local governments in the West Africa except",
A: "shortage of trained personnel",
B: "obtaining loans form banks",
C: "nepotism",
D: "corruption",
answer: "B. Administrative officers were in short supply",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. A British colony means",
A: "a territory endowed with arable farm land",
B: "an area for colonial plantation",
C: "an area directly under the control of the traditional rulers and chiefs",
D: "a territory acquired by the colonialists through settlement or conquest",
answer: "C. the British failed to give qualitative education to Africans",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Which of the following was not a reason for the adoption of indirect Rule in British West African territories?",
A: "The chiefs approved of it",
B: "Administrative officers were in short supply",
C: "there was insufficient funding",
D: "the traditional rulers commanded respect among their subjects",
answer: "A. the end of colonial rule",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. A major disadvantage of the Indirect Rule System was that he",
A: "economy was over industrialized",
B: "appointments were based on qualification",
C: "British failed to give qualitative education to Africans",
D: "central administration was dominated by Africans",
answer: "A. absorption of French colonial ex-servicemen into the French army",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. The organ of the United Nations Organization that coordinates the activities of its specialized agencies the",
A: "General Assembly",
B: "International Court of Justice",
C: "Economic and Social Council",
D: "Trusteeship Council",
answer: "C. Economic and Social Council",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. The primary objective of the United Nations Organization (UNO) is to",
A: "stop aggression",
B: "help poor countries",
C: "fight against injustice",
D: "maintain world peace",
answer: "D. maintain world peace",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following international organizations did all West African countries belong to?",
A: "Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries",
B: "North Atlantic Treaty Organization",
C: "European Union",
D: "Organization of African Unity",
answer: "D. Organization of African Unity",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the following is not an organ of the Organization of African Unity (OAU)? The",
A: "Assembly of Heads of State and Government",
B: "Tribunal of the Community",
C: "Council of Ministers",
D: "Secretariat",
answer: "B. Tribunal of the Community",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. *******************************",
A: "*******************************",
B: "*******************************",
C: "*******************************",
D: "*******************************",
answer: "Z. zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
correctLetter: "Z",
correctOption: 9,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The headquarters of the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) Fund for Cooperation Compensation and Development is located in",
A: "Lome",
B: "Lagos",
C: "Accra",
D: "Dakar",
answer: "B. Lagos",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},


]